<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on Sin(x)</title>
    <link>https://sinanthahir.github.io/tags/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on Sin(x)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sinanthahir.github.io/tags/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How Project Aria going to change everyday life</title>
      <link>https://sinanthahir.github.io/blogs/project-aria-wearable-ar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sinanthahir.github.io/blogs/project-aria-wearable-ar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-project-aria-going-to-change-everyday-life--facebooks-wearable-ar&#34;&gt;How Project Aria going to change everyday life : Facebook’s Wearable AR&lt;/h2&gt;






    
    


&lt;div class=&#34;rounded p-3 my-6&#34; style=&#34;background-color: #d9edf7; color: #31708f;&#34; &gt;
    
“ Augmented Reality — Enhancing flow of everyday life ”

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook’s Full AR glasses are much away from reaching to our hands, but had started there road-test mapping with Cluster of sensors or to particularly say a ‘Sensory array’ debut research device in Seattle and the San Francisco Bay Area. A group of 100 Facebook employees and others getting hands on these, testing and for the thrive for data collection. The company announced the news Wednesday at its virtual &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebookconnect.com/en&#34;&gt;Facebook Connect&lt;/a&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-what-is-this-project-aria-&#34;&gt;So what is this PROJECT ARIA ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Project Aria, Facebook’s Reality Labs is trying to vision a future device free flow into the everyday life expect for the pair of glasses. these are not just the ordinary glasses, but a Augmented Reality Wearable. As Facebook says these pair of glasses adds a 3D layer of useful, relevant and meaningful information on top of our physical world. they projects out examples like- “Imagine calling a friend and chatting with their lifelike avatar across the table. Imagine a digital assistant smart enough to detect road hazards, offer up stats during a business meeting, or even help you hear better in a noisy environment”. It paves the way for doing the everyday task at a better way and opens up an entirely new way of moving through the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NNPMEU6OqIs&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oculus.com/quest-2/&#34;&gt;Oculus Quest 2&lt;/a&gt; an advanced stand-alone VR headset, is one of the Facebook’s Current Immersive Product on the market. But there AR ambition are going much a further way; The company is looking forward in creating a spatial scan of the real word called &lt;a href=&#34;https://about.fb.com/realitylabs/projectaria/&#34;&gt;Live Map&lt;/a&gt; which will in-turn creates a better relation with people and other objects, giving a sense to the device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Facebook’s Reality Lab envisions to provide a better connectivity with no look downs to your devices. They are looking to a world where the device itself disappears in to the flow of life. Thus Project Aria is a new research project that will help us build the first generation of wearable AR devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tdj9U0pyem4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook says “To actually build glasses flexible enough to work for most face shapes and sizes, and create the software to support them, we still need &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.theinformation.com/articles/facebooks-chief-scientist-mass-adoption-of-ar-is-years-away&#34;&gt;several generations of breakthroughs&lt;/a&gt;, like systems to enhance audio and visual input, contextualized AI, and a lightweight frame to house it all”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-visionary-research-tool-&#34;&gt;A visionary research tool !&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook puts into light that ‘The Project Aria glasses are not a consumer product, nor are they a prototype’ but a step into the future step in AR efforts. They are looking forward for a research device that will help us understand how to build the software and hardware necessary for AR glasses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zue1pxGJnvg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Project Aria glasses use sensors to capture video and audio from the wearer’s point of view, as well as eye movement and location data to help our engineers and programmers figure out how AR glasses can work in practice.but that information will be held on-device and not be seen by Facebook researchers before blurring the data of faces and sensitive information like car license plates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook plans to train an AI Assistant adapted for the glasses usage through the smart spatial audio technology. they also plans in refining the Livemaps; which will provide a 3D array of data and be a backbone for navigation through these glasses.They are practically improving the concept of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ai.facebook.com/blog/new-milestones-in-embodied-ai/&#34;&gt;embodied AI&lt;/a&gt; through these glasses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the first test run is set offed, Project Aria glasses are initially be made available to a limited group of Facebook employees and contractors in the United States, trained in both where and when to use the device, and where and when not to. Project Aria is most definitely not an actual pair of smartglasses. It’s a “sensor array” for those future glasses. Facebook’s post on Aria says it will have “the full sensor suite used in VR headsets for spatial awareness,” adding, “they also compute location from GPS, take high-res pictures, and capture multichannel audio and eye images”. But the intersection of the real world and the data-collecting challenges smartglasses pose sounds like an extremely tricky problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;privacy-matters-&#34;&gt;Privacy Matters !&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook is promising to take care with data on the glasses. The testers are reportedly being instructed on how to use these devices responsibly. But the glasses will be tested lots of public spaces. In privately owned public places they’re supposed to get consent before recording. The data being recorded is encrypted and then Facebook uses a “secure ingestion system to upload data from the devices to a separate, designated storage space, accessible only to researchers with approved access.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public-collected data will “not be used to inform the ads people see across Facebook’s apps,” Facebook’s Project Aria privacy guidelines say. But that also suggests that, eventually, information on AR headsets could be used to target ads. It would be dealt with in the near AR future amidst not now. You can view the &lt;a href=&#34;https://about.fb.com/realitylabs/projectaria/privacy-policy/&#34;&gt;privacy policy&lt;/a&gt; guidelines by Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenges&#34;&gt;Challenges!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook say’s “The biggest initial challenge they are facing is to finding a way to take all of the existing sensors necessary to make AR work, and fitting them on a pair of glasses that participants could actually wear.” not only the design specification but also a more number of problem to be solved like Heat dissipated from micro-computers used, better wireless connectivity provision, light weight frames, better battery life to run all day long, a framework for storing and indexing your virtual objects( virtual co-ordinates ) placed by the user to another user’s view, preparing a well developed navigation which see’s better and understand the surroundings ; as a wearable, the contrast ratio correction as moving from sun to dark workplaces, varying focal lengths suitable for various peoples, better field view even with the 3D layer infographics . As Bosworth says “This is a playground of challenging problems” , yes purely a many number solution is yet need to be founded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;looking-forward&#34;&gt;Looking Forward&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook in one hand is really looking for providing an evolutionary research in AR — making a better flow in the everyday life. Though the privacy matters are really a complicated weird line, if it is from Facebook. However the Facebook’s view “for a world with fewer devices and more time spent enjoying moments with family and friends, where opportunity is defined by passions, not geography or circumstance” sounds like a better tomorrow .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more details about &lt;strong&gt;Project Aria&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://about.fb.com/realitylabs/projectaria/&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article was also published in &lt;a href=&#34;https://sinanthahir.medium.com/how-project-aria-going-to-change-everyday-life-facebooks-wearable-ar-3428222e5cf1&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;. You can check out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://sinanthahir.medium.com/&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; page too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>