<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Notes on Sin(x)</title>
    <link>https://sinanthahir.github.io/notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Notes on Sin(x)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sinanthahir.github.io/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Better Decision from Bitter Opinions</title>
      <link>https://sinanthahir.github.io/notes/better-decision-bitter-opinions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sinanthahir.github.io/notes/better-decision-bitter-opinions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-decision-from-bitter-opinions-&#34;&gt;Better Decision from Bitter Opinions !&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why criticism is good for you !&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;cover09.png&#34; alt=&#34;cover&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Criticism&lt;/strong&gt; means the expression of disagreement of someone or something that is based on perceived beliefs, faults and mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the point is to consider whether it’s good or not. Taking criticism can be a difficult thing. Nobody likes to be told that something they have slaved over for days didn’t quite hit the mark. If we go by it’s meaning; to criticize someone is bad and even if you know some of your work probably deserved some extra love, criticism always stings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on the other hand, it may lead to improvement of the person being criticized and he becoming a better person, not repeating the mistakes again. At some point, even my writings — &lt;em&gt;are so dependant on reviews and opinions&lt;/em&gt;. Though one day you will encounter a customer or your audience and even a reviewer — who wants to tell you how to do things better. But it’s not all bad news because sometimes you can use criticism to give you a competitive edge. It entirely depends upon the perceived value hidden behind the criticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;criticism--a-form-of-communication&#34;&gt;Criticism : a form of communication.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone has a criticism for you; literally take it as they want to give you a feedback on what you are done or doing for them. &lt;strong&gt;We all make mistakes all the time, it is human nature&lt;/strong&gt;. As we go through life we have plenty of opportunity to learn and improve ourselves. That means Criticism is an opportunity to learn more about the person who you’re working for and in case your a influencer or in business; how to convert them into a satisfied customer or audience member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Any fool can criticize, condemn, and complain but it takes character and self control to be understanding and forgiving.&lt;/em&gt;” — &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dalecarnegie.com/en&#34;&gt;Dale Carnegie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, there may be some truth behind each criticism you get; even it is given out on spite and bitterness. The criticism aimed at you may not make sense at the time, It is often the case that a slight change on your character is a fair reflection of how another person sees you at that point in time. So take a step-back, try to look from other’s perspective or ask the opinions of a honest friend, that will make you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;criticism--gives-you-a-competitive-advantage&#34;&gt;Criticism : gives you a Competitive advantage.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You cannot be sure whatever the critic is saying is right. Having heard him out, compare his statements or assessments with the facts on the ground. Sort out what is true from what is a biased statement and make objective analysis of them.
Think about it : if you are a Salesperson and can get a customer to tell you — and just you — how to give them the perfect product or service, that’s information you’ve got that no one else has. Even being a criticism too, the information you gets, puts you at an advantage over anyone else in your sector and can be used again in the future to get things right, even faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are open to suggestions around how you might approach things differently, you’ll be perceived as a more authentic leader and it’ll be easier for you to rally a team around a common goal or towards improving shared processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;think-before-act&#34;&gt;Think Before Act.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t take it personally if someone doesn’t immediately like your work. Not everyone has pure motives when it comes to giving you feedback. If the criticism you’re receiving really stings, think about what that person is saying. &lt;em&gt;Are they talking about something that directly influences the way you work or your behavior in a specific situation? Or are they more concerned about you come off as a person?&lt;/em&gt; The key thing to remember is that whatever the circumstance is, don´t respond in anger as this will cause a scene and create bad feelings — and possibly a bad image of you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;em&gt;when people tell you something’s wrong or doesn’t work for them, they are almost always right. When they tell you exactly what they think is wrong and how to fix it, they are almost always wrong.&lt;/em&gt; — &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.neilgaiman.com/&#34;&gt;Neil Gaiman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will be occasions when you feel the criticism is personal and, now and then, you’ll be right.If feedback is based on something intrinsic to your personality, it’s not important enough to worry about. Criticism needs to be partnered with a solution to help you correct the action. If it’s not, the person is not interested in helping enough to warrant getting involved, literally it’s enough for them to shut up.They are also able to make it work to their advantage or, if all else fails, politely conclude the partnership and leave with their reputation intact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsure of how effectively you’re communicating? Try to transform your critical phrases into feedback that inspires change. May these words help you along !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas, Enjoy reading !&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is it okay to show your Flaws</title>
      <link>https://sinanthahir.github.io/notes/is-it-okay-to-show-your-flaws/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sinanthahir.github.io/notes/is-it-okay-to-show-your-flaws/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;is-it-okay-to-show-your-flaws&#34;&gt;Is it okay to show your Flaws&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;when-and-how-i-fall-in-love-with-my-flaws-&#34;&gt;When and how, i Fall in Love with My Flaws !&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;01.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;img&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us are taught to hide our flaws. the fact is that each one of us from the childhood to the very existence of life; try to preserve our flaws and insecurities. but not a single one of us is perfect. And that’s one of the great thing of the life. Not only we do have flaws, but each of us struggles with feeling flawed at some situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a entrepreneur, i too had many time flawed. All the adrenaline shot up in the head, at the time of brain-storming sections. As a core member, the idea’s or for the suggestion’s — i need them intact or rather say; to be good. But for me,‘how to convey properly’ , or ‘how to make others understand’ , all of a sudden such thoughts came to hit me, when standing in front of them. One of the colleague said, it was overthinking, that make me do so, but really need to appreciate her for hearing me out, cause overthinking is one of my flaws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes ! Even now when i’m writing it, i’m indeed flawed! i don’t know how much my idea is going to lay impact on you. Now, you may be thinking me, being a dumb ass over-thinker; Haha, though some time these flaws really in-turns out to be good. Frankly at many times, these over-thoughts turned my strategic action very beneficial. That was the moment, made me to fall in love with my flaws. May be some of you had already accepted there flaws or some are still cliche to there flaws. To say, there will some times, when you really love it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lets-talk-about-wabi-sabi&#34;&gt;Lets talk about Wabi-Sabi.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If my analogy hadn’t able to ‘hit a hole’ for you, lets try a different approach.
In Japanese culture, there is an art form known as &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.utne.com/mind-and-body/wabi-sabi&#34;&gt;wabi-sabi&lt;/a&gt;. It has been around for centuries. When a plate becomes chipped or cracked, it is not discarded like trash. The cracks are filled with metallic materials to accentuate their details. Wabi-sabi celebrates imperfections because no two are exactly the same. You possess that uniqueness in your own life, and you should be proud of what it’s helped you become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course we all know how difficult it is to accept flaws. It’s a difficult thing to do when it comes to other people and when it comes to ourselves, well, it’s can seem nearly impossible. But, hard as it might seem, it is possible to love even the most flaws and it’s much essential to live a positive present life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But to live so, First learn to love yourself for who you are!
Loving yourself means loving even the not-so-great parts of yourself. Learning to love your flaws is going to be a constant battle, but that is a worth a fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;so-lets-get-to-know-how-to-fall-in-love-with-your-flaw&#34;&gt;So lets get to know how to fall in love with your Flaw.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-look-for-something-you-can-do-about-it&#34;&gt;1. Look For Something you can do about it.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foremost, you need to check whether if the flaws troubling is something you can actually do something for it, in case of flaws like — bad temper or wicked impatience should not be accepted instead should work on. It’s not like throwing up your hands and saying, “Oh, that’s the way I am!”. Ask Yourself : Does the flaw negatively impact you and others? Is there anything I can do to change it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-determine-your-actually-going-to-do-something&#34;&gt;2. Determine your actually going to do something.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only you know and you only will know, deep down whether the flaw bugs you or not, now it’s time to be brutally honest with yourself. If you’ve determined that a flaw is to be changed. You can change it, but will you ? If you know it needs to be changed and you’re going to put in the effort, awesome! Go for it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-view-it-in-others-perspective&#34;&gt;3. View it in other’s Perspective.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re so close to our flaws that they seem so much larger to us, i.e magnified by our own perception. The things you see as horrible or offensive might not look so bad when you try seeing them from an outsider’s point of view. In your mind, take a step back and try to imagine from other’s perspective about the flaw. When it comes, consider and contemplate how you would react to it when it is spotted on someone else. There you gets the clear image of your flaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;4-accept-for-really-what-it-is&#34;&gt;4. Accept for really what it is.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, accept your flaw for exactly what it is. After viewing from other person view and understanding about the flaw, now it’s time to take one step further — simply accept it for what it is. Don’t compare it to others or rate it on a scale of good/bad. Strip it from all internal judgments; Accept it for what it is and realize that it is a part of you. Your flaws make you who you are, so embrace them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you should be on the road to either changing or loving your flaws, these steps allowed me to accept my flaws. Only you will know which flaw you should be working on and which one you need to accept and love. Remember Everyone has something, may be many he or she is flawed. But only Some people proactively choose to accept and love them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be one among them. &lt;strong&gt;Love Your Flaws&lt;/strong&gt; !&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Write a book: Atleast one in your lifetime.</title>
      <link>https://sinanthahir.github.io/notes/writebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sinanthahir.github.io/notes/writebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;write-a-book-at-least-one-in-your-lifetime&#34;&gt;Write a book: At least one in your lifetime.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;youll-discover-who-you-are-unless-youve-tried-it&#34;&gt;You’ll discover who you are; unless you’ve tried it.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;undraw.svg&#34; alt=&#34;undraw&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in this world with 7.8 Billion others, you hear that number; each individual with there own life story and putting each one’s creativeness forward to paper in your solace; can actually be a relief and thus a new writer is born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing a book considered as a skill but for me it’s upskilling. Listen, everyone can be a writer. Each one of us have a story to share. In fact, more stories to put forward. But the truth to write these stories, first &lt;strong&gt;you need to start write&lt;/strong&gt;. Here come the prior stepping stones– &lt;strong&gt;Dedication and Passion&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By its very nature, Writing is an introspective and thoughtful activity. You don’t have to complete a book in a month or two; take your time. The more time you take in writing, the more you experience. If you’re an amateur, starting to write — go for &lt;strong&gt;your trajectory of life&lt;/strong&gt;. Many people think they need to do something massive or be famous to write about their life, That’s not truth at all. The reason behind writing about your life is that you have a real story; something worth changing lives of others with your trial and tribulations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even you aren’t ready for a memoir, thou still have a valuable piece of short influential timeline, experiences or the knowledge gained that can help others; can be pen downed. It’s &lt;strong&gt;hard to peek inside&lt;/strong&gt;, one of the hardest things in our life is to look inside ourselves. The harder you self-reflect, the more you discover who you been these all time. It can be objected a time when &lt;strong&gt;we evaluate ourselves&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;not-to-mention-writing-a-memoir&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not to mention writing a memoir.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing to write a book about yourself is to get really, really &lt;strong&gt;honest&lt;/strong&gt; and dig into the raw and deep parts about yourself. Nobody wants a book about you that’s all sunshine and rainbows because that’s not real life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;if-youre-writing-about-yourself-here-are-some-tips&#34;&gt;If You’re writing about yourself, here are some tips.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Decide what you need to write about yourself or a part of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Self-reflect your own life&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Specify the experiences you want to share&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a mind-map of experience to connect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take those ideas and starts to write an outline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through writing, you’ll &lt;em&gt;gain perspective&lt;/em&gt; towards what really matters you. It will also teach you, &lt;strong&gt;the unique value of your own willpower&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing a book is a way to touch your thoughts, values, and motivations. This simple act of writing can perish to measure the depths of your discipline and efforts. Because, writing is cheaper than a therapy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that counts is that you get your first word on paper, and then a word after that. You owe it to yourself to explore your passion and write a book. When you’re writing about something you love, it won’t feel like work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes the hectic, tasks of drafting and publishing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A shady statistic, only 1% of world population ever publishes a book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what you write a book about, whether you published it or not; that you write will open the door to your inwards or for more ideas. You’ll educate yourself on a broad array of ideas to tackle more obstacles, Life thrown at you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing a book is leaving your comfort zone. &lt;strong&gt;The only way you grow as a person is by forcing yourself to leave your comfort zone.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to touch the sky — &lt;strong&gt;write a book yourselves. Discover who you really are&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was original published on &lt;a href=&#34;https://sinanthahir.medium.com/write-a-book-at-least-one-in-your-lifetime-971e73eb4e1c&#34;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; dated Sep 15, 2020. If you can check my Medium space.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>